Guide to the John Owen papers 1850-1871
Montana Historical Society
John Owen papers
1850-1871
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 44
Owen, John, 1818-1889
.75 linear feet of shelf space
John Owen (1818-1889), a pioneer fur trader in the Northwest, built Fort Owen in the Bitterroot Valley, Montana Territory, and served as a special agent for the Flathead Indians. Collection contains diaries and journals (1850-1871); a combined register of births, deaths, and marriages of Fort Owen residents; a letterpress book (1858-1859); an account book (1850-1860) for trade at Fort Owen, which also contains accounts (1876-1889) for some other firm; and a bill of sale (1850) for the land on which the St. Mary's Mission was built.
A native of Pennsylvania, born in 1818, John Owen first came to what is now Montana as a sutler for Colonel Loring's Oregon-bound column. In 1850, he purchased the site of St. Mary's Mission from Jesuit missionaries, and there built his trading post, Fort Owen. Owen operated his post as a trading center for white trappers and Indians of the area, and his fort also served as a way station to an increasing influx of settlers. Fort Owen contained the first commercial grist mill in the area and served other important functions. In 1856, because of his special relationship with the Flathead Indians, Owen was appointed special agent to that tribe and its affiliates. He held this position until 1862. Owen's mind began to fail in the early 1870s, and he was hospitalized in Helena until 1877, when he was transferred to the care of relatives in Philadelphia. He died there on July 12, 1889.
This collection contains sixteen diaries, detailing John Owen's life and his many excursions throughout the Northwest (1850-1871). Also, there are a register of births, deaths, and marriages; (1858-1860); copied outgoing letters (1858-1859); and an account book for trade at Fort Owen (1850-1860). This last volume also was used for mercantile and farm accounts (1876-1889), possibly by the Fort's subsequent owner, Washington J. McCormick.
:
Arranged by series
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Owen, John, 1818-1889
Fort Owen (Mont.); St. Mary's Mission (Mont.)
Frontier and pioneer life--Montana; Fur trade--Montana; Trading posts--Montana; Vital statistics--Montana; Overland journeys to Montana
Montana; Pioneers; Overland Journeys to the Northwestern United States
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Biographical Materials
  - Letters of information re John Owen [from Mary Winslett; library staff], 1922 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Incoming Correspondence
  - J.W. Denver; Phillip H. Sheridan, 1873 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- Outgoing Correspondence
  - "Fort Owen Register and Letter Book 1858 and 1859"; miscellaneous, 1858-1860, 1869 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence
  - U.S. Deptartment of Interior to Benjamin F. Potts re John Owen land claim, 1875 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Diaries
  - "Journey from Fort Owen via Fort Hall to Walla Walla in 1851"; "Diary and A/c Book of Ft. Owen in 1851 and 1852"; "Diary of a Journey from Ft. Owen to the Dalles in 1852", 1851-1852 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - "Journey from Ft. Owen to Salmon River & Return in 1854"; "Diary of a Journey from the Dalles to Ft. Owen in 1854"; "Fort Owen Journal 1854-1855" (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - "Fort Owen Diary for 1856"; "Fort Owen Journal 1857 and 1858"; "Diary of a trip from Walla Walla to Fort Owen in 1857.--Also of return trip to Walla Walla in 1858", 1856-1858 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - "Diary of a Journey to Ft. Benton in 1858"; "Fort Owen Journal 1860-1861"; "Fort Owen Diary, M.T. 1862, 1863 & part of 1865", 1858-1865 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - "Diary of a Journey from Fort Owen to Walla Walla in 1863, etc. etc."; "Diary of a Journey from the North Plate [Platte] to Montana in 1864", 1863-1864 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - "Fort Owen diary for 1865, 1866 & 1867"; untitled diary, 1865-1871 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
- Financial Records
  - "Fort Owen a/c Book", 1850-1860, 1876-1889 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
- Legal Documents
  - "Application for Admission of Maj. Jno. Owen, Insane, to the Territorial Hospital, Lewis & Clarke Co.", 1874 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Bill of sale for land on which Fort Owen was built, 1850 (Box-folder 2 / 4)